{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The remnants of this government established the Republic of Ezo after losing the Boshin War. Two and a half centuries earlier, this government was founded after its leader won the Battle of Sekigahara against the Toyotomi clan. This government’s policy of sakoku came to an end when Matthew Perry’s Black Ships forced the opening of Japan through the 1854 Convention of Kanagawa. For ten points, name this last Japanese shogunate.",
      "answer": "Tokugawa Shogunate or Tokugawa Bakufu"
    },
    {
      "question": "Xenophon’s Anabasis describes ten thousand Greek soldiers of this type who fought Artaxerxes II of Persia. A war named for these people was won by Hamilcar Barca and led to his conquest of Spain. Famed soldiers of this type include slingers from Rhodes and archers from Crete. Greeks who fought for Persia were, for ten points, what type of soldier that fought not for national pride, but for money?",
      "answer": "mercenary"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most prominent of the Townshend Acts not to be repealed in 1770 was a tax levied on this commodity. The Dartmouth, the Eleanor, and the Beaver carried this commodity from England to the American colonies. The Intolerable Acts were passed in response to the dumping of this commodity into a Massachusetts Harbor in 1773 by members of the Sons of Liberty. For ten points, identify this commodity destroyed in a namesake Boston party.",
      "answer": [
        "tea",
        "Tea Act",
        "Boston Tea Party"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This location is the setting of a photo of a boy holding a toy hand grenade by Diane Arbus. Over 7,500 vinyl frames were adorned with saffron nylon fabric during a Christo and Jeanne-Claude exhibit at this location known as The Gates. Belvedere Castle and the Strawberry Fields memorial to John Lennon are located in this park, which was outlined in the Greensward Plan by Calvert Vaux [voh] and Frederick Law Olmsted. For ten points, name this large park in Manhattan.",
      "answer": "Central Park"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Bazalgette designed this city’s sewer system, which reduced the frequency of cholera outbreaks and prevented a recurrence of the 1858 “Great Stink.” This city was one of first sites for rubber to be grown outside of South America, as part of a botanical research project at Kew. This city’s Crystal Palace stood in its Hyde Park until 1936 and was opened in 1851 by Queen Victoria. Sewage was once pumped into the River Thames in, for ten points, what capital city of England?",
      "answer": "London"
    },
    {
      "question": "On this island, a 5th century BC law code inscribed on circular walls can be seen in ruins in Gortyn. This island is home to a distinctive type of pottery known as the “kamares ware,” examples of which are on display in Heraklion. The Thera volcanic eruption may have ended a civilization on this island, where frescos depicting a bull-leaping motif are common at the palace of Knossos. For ten points, name this largest Greek island, the center of the Minoan civilization.",
      "answer": "Crete"
    },
    {
      "question": "A former Speaker of this state’s House of Representatives ran for the Senate in 2010, beating Kendrick Meek and Charlie Crist. A Congresswoman from this state resigned as DNC chair after a scandal involving Wikileaks and her hacked emails. Rick Scott governs, for ten points, what swing state that was represented by Debbie Wasserman Schultz in the House and is currently represented in the Senate by Marco Rubio?",
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "question": "Anna Chennault arranged a meeting for this man with Ambassador Bui Diem that violated the Logan Act. Charles Colson admitted this man had told him that a typewriter was fabricated in the Alger Hiss case. This politician sabotaged peace talks in Vietnam in the aforementioned Chennault affair, promising better results after this man defeated Hubert Humphrey in the 1968 election. For ten points, name this US President who withdrew the US from Vietnam in 1973.",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2015, a yearly pillow fight at this location was banned after hard objects were stuffed in pillow cases, leading to two dozen injuries. This location was connected to Constitution Island by a long chain in its original design by Tadeusz Kosciuszko [tah-dah-oosh ko-SHOO-skoh]. The longest continuously occupied American military post is, for ten points, what New York location, the base of the U.S. Military Academy, which was to be betrayed by Benedict Arnold?",
      "answer": [
        "West Point",
        "the US Military Academy until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Domus Conversorum was a residence specifically built to house these people, many of whom died when Clifford’s Tower, the keep of York Castle, was burned to the ground in 1190. Oliver Cromwell ended a policy whereby these people had been banned from England since the reign of Edward I. The Balfour Declaration pledged support for the creation of a homeland for these people in the Middle East. For ten points, name this religious group whose British members have included Benjamin Disraeli.",
      "answer": "Jewish people"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a novel set in this country, Aurora de Gama falls in love with the manager at her father’s spice warehouse; that novel takes its name from the dying reaction of Boabdil and is titled The Moor’s Last Sigh. A group of telepathic youths hold a conference in this country in a novel in which Saleem Sinai was born at the exact moment of this country’s independence. For ten points, name this setting of Salman Rushdie’s novel Midnight’s Children.",
        "answer": "India"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rushdie’s Satanic Verses prompted this Supreme Leader of Iran to issue a fatwa against him in 1989.",
        "answer": "Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In his early military career, this man was given the honor of escorting the captured chief Black Hawk. Officials picked for this man’s Cabinet included Stephen Mallory and Judah Benjamin. His vice president, Alexander Stephens, stated that this man’s government was founded “upon the great truth” of racial inequality. Command of the Army of Northern Virginia was given to Robert E. Lee by, for ten points, what only president of the Confederate States of America?",
        "answer": "Jefferson Davis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Judah Benjamin was the first man to hold this post in the Confederate cabinet; the analogous honor in the United States was claimed by Edmund Randolph.",
        "answer": [
          "Confederate and/or US Attorney General",
          "descriptions of the head of the Department of Justice"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hedonistic white settlers settled this country’s Happy Valley. This country subsidized possibly non-existent gold in the Goldenberg Scandal. This country’s Kalenjin people came to power under Daniel Arap Moi, who discriminated against its Kikuyu ethnic group. This country’s Westgate shopping mall was attacked in 2013 by Al-Shabaab, a terrorist group based in neighboring Somalia. For ten points, name this east African country led by Uhuru Kenyatta.",
        "answer": "Kenya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dedan Kimathi led the Kikuyu people in this 1950s uprising against British colonial power in Kenya.",
        "answer": "Mau Mau Rebellion"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s mothax were allowed to fight, but denied the right to join in communal banquets where a black broth was served. Every autumn in this city, the krypteia were permitted to slaughter slaves to prevent events like the Messenian Wars and other helot uprisings. This city’s agoge [uh-goh-gay] system trained boys from the age of 7 into this city’s elite military. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state whose army fought Athens in the Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Sparta or Lacedaemonia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This semi-mythical Spartan lawgiver, a mothax himself, establishedthe agoge educational system and undertook currency and land reform.",
        "answer": "Lycurgus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1341, a holder of this title instituted a salt tax called the gabelle. This title was promised to Henry V at the Treaty of Troyes and was split from the Kingdom of Navarre by Joan II. The next holder of this position was known as the dauphin. After 987, holders of this position were descended from Hugh Capet. For ten points, name this royal title held by eighteen different men with regnal name Louis.",
        "answer": "King of France"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The gabelle salt tax was abolished by this legislative body, which was formed by members of the Third Estate in summer 1789 in the buildup to the French Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "National Assembly or Assembl´ee Nationale",
          "National Constituent Assembly",
          "Assembl´ee Nationale Constituante"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Demilitarization along this border was planned by the Rush-Bagot Treaty. Confusion over this border led to a bloodless war after a pig was shot on San Juan Island. Lumberjack infighting along this border led to the Aroostook War, which was ended by a treaty negotiated by Daniel Webster. This border was initially demarcated by the 1783 Treaty of Paris following the American Revolution. For ten points, name this border whose eastern end lies between Maine and New Brunswick.",
        "answer": [
          "the border between Canada and the United States of America",
          "USA",
          "America for United States"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Aroostook War was ended by a treaty signed by, and named for, Daniel Webster and this British baron.",
        "answer": "Alexander Baring, 1st Baron Ashburton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A text written in a prison in Zakopane [zah-ko-pahn-eh] during this war was used for the second movement of Henryk Gorecki’s Symphony of Sorrowful Songs. A symphony written during this war contains a passage parodying a Franz Lehar tune over a snare drum in its depiction of soldiers invading the title city. For ten points, name this war in which Dmitry Shostakovich wrote his Seventh Symphony, depicting the siege of Leningrad by Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "World War II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another musical composition inspired by World War II was a dissonant Krzysztof Penderecki [chris-toff pen-der-etz-kee] piece for 52 strings entitled Threnody to the Victims of what city?",
        "answer": "Threnody to the Victims of Hiroshima"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Clausius’inequalitywasanearlyformulationofalawconcerningthisquantity,whosepublicawareness grew through Isaac Asimov’s short story “The Last Question.” Early theories on this quantity were developed by Lazare Carnot [la-zarr car-noh], whose namesake cycle conserves this quantity. Ludwig Boltzmann’s tombstone has an equation for this quantity engraved on it. According to the second law of thermodynamics, this quantity always increases within isolated systems. For ten points, name this measure of disorder within a system.",
        "answer": "entropy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The second law of thermodynamics inspired this Czechoslovakian dissident, who wrote that “the basic law of life is to be ever more highly structured and to struggle against entropy” in an open letter to Gustav Husak in 1975. This writer became President of Czechoslovakia in 1989.",
        "answer": "V´aclav Havel"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The New Deal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global economic downturn that the New Deal counteracted.",
          "answer": "Great Depression"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who formulated the New Deal.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "New Deal program that provides an old age pension and now includes disability benefits.",
          "answer": [
            "Social Security",
            "additional information"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed plan to save the New Deal by manipulating the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": [
            "court packing",
            "anything related to adding more justices to the Supreme Court"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist for the WPA who captured the Migrant Mother photo.",
          "answer": "Dorothea Lange"
        },
        {
          "question": "State electrified by a namesake “Valley Authority” led by David Lilienthal.",
          "answer": "Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic concept suspended in the New Deal and ended by the later Bretton Woods conference, allowing the convertibility of a precious metal to dollars.",
          "answer": "gold standard do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Advisor and Commerce Secretary who oversaw the Civil Works Administration and the Works Progress Administration.",
          "answer": "Harry Hopkins"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Roman Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the Roman who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was assassinated in 44 BC after proclaiming himself dictator four years earlier.",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became the first emperor of Rome.",
          "answer": [
            "Augustus Caesar or Octavian",
            "Gaius Octavius",
            "Gaius Octavianus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the Stoic work Meditations and was the last of the Five Good Emperors.",
          "answer": "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied with Cassius at the Battle of Philippi, where he was defeated by the Second Triumvirate?",
          "answer": "Marcus Junius Brutus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated the Mediterranean pirates before joining the First Triumvirate.",
          "answer": "Pompey the Great or Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Died invading Parthia at the Battle of Carrhae and was known as the richest man in Rome.",
          "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated the Sicilian Revolt and governed Africa as a member of the Second Triumvirate.",
          "answer": "Marcus Aemilius Lepidus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Followed his brother Gaius, both in pushing for land reforms and being assassinated by senators.",
          "answer": "Tiberius Gracchus the Younger"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "River that nourished ancient Egyptian culture and is divided into “white” and “blue” portions.",
          "answer": "Nile River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Species of dung beetle worshipped by the ancient Egyptians.",
          "answer": [
            "scarab",
            "scarabaeus sacer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pharaoh who died at the age of 18 and whose tomb was discovered in 1922 by Howard Carter.",
          "answer": [
            "King Tutankhamun",
            "King Tutankhaten"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian symbol of “life,” resembling a cross with a handle, that is carried in depictions of almost every Egyptian pharaoh.",
          "answer": "ankh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Thutmose II who served as the second female pharaoh in history.",
          "answer": "Hatshepsut"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal necropolis opposite Thebes, a major burial site that contains 63 discovered tombs of pharaohs and Egyptian nobles.",
          "answer": [
            "Valley of the Kings",
            "Wadi al Muluk"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pharaoh who established a sun-worshipping cult in the 14th century BC.",
          "answer": "Akhenaten or Amenhotep IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where that sun-worshipping cult was centered, and which names a style of New Kingdom art.",
          "answer": [
            "Amarna",
            "Akhetaten"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2015, members of this group noted “It. Just. Isn’t. That. Good.” in their two-star review of In the Aeroplane Over the Sea by Neutral Milk Hotel. That review was labeled “Disgusting” by a website that later praised a State Department effort to counter this group: a world map with the US (20 pts)",
        "shrunk to be too small for this group to find. In real life, a member of this group used the caption “We respawn in Jannah” in an (10 pts)",
        "Instagram post referencing Call of Duty, one of its numerous recruitment attempts over social media. Clickhole.com frequently lampoons, for ten points, what terrorist group that lost control of Mosul in July 2017?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ISIS or Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
        "or ISIL",
        "or Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
        "or Daesh",
        "descriptions of Clickhole.com’s version of ISIS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization used a sacred messenger vehicle called the Paralus. This organization, which was wiped out after the Battle of Aegospotami, was based at (20 pts)",
        "Piraeus, a city guarded by the Long Walls. This organization withdrew from the Battle of Cape Artemisium and later won the decisive Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Salamis, driving the Persians from Greece. Themistocles advocated for the expansion of, for ten points, what military force whose triremes ensured the Delian League’s control of the Aegean Sea?"
      ],
      "answer": "navy of ancient Athens"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The memorial site of Castle Hill in this region is sometimes named after Alexander Baranov, who established a provisional capital here in the early 1800s after defeating Tlingit natives. This region’s ports of (20 pts)",
        "Dyea and Skagway boomed in the 1890s as through points for gold prospectors. Sitka was the (10 pts)",
        "Russian territorial capital of this region, which was acquired by the U.S. in 1867 in a move dubbed Seward’s Folly. For ten points, name this modern US state home to the cities of Fairbanks and Anchorage."
      ],
      "answer": "Alaska"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Luxembourg Compromise ended this leader’s withdrawal from the European Economic Community during the Empty Chair Crisis. In another role, this leader advocated for a mobile professional force in The (20 pts)",
        "Army of the Future, panning his nation’s usage of the Maginot Line. After Philippe (10 pts)",
        "Petain took power as the head of the Vichy puppet state, this man led his country’s “Free” forces against the Nazis during World War II. For ten points, name this first president of the French Fifth Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A modern native indigenous to this country is nicknamed “Man of the Hole” due to the large, 6-feet deep holes he digs to trap prey. Claude Levi-Strauss’s Triste Tropiques [treest troh-PEEK] focuses primarily on this non-Asian country, which recently surpassed New (20 pts)",
        "Guinea in having the most uncontacted peoples within its borders. Shantytowns called “favelas” dot the urban landscape of cities like (10 pts)",
        "Sao Paolo and Rio de Janeiro in, for ten points, what Portuguese-speaking South American country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Planes intercepted over this facility are often forced to land in nearby Hagerstown. This facility is officially designated NSF Thurmont and was known as “Shangri-La” in the (20 pts)",
        "1940s. In 1978, this facility hosted meetings that created two frameworks: the first was condemned by the UN, but the second earned (10 pts)",
        "Menachim Began and Anwar Sadat a shared Nobel Prize. For ten points, name this Maryland facility, a Presidential retreat where Jimmy Carter hosted Middle East peace talks that produced a set of Accords. ANSWER:Camp David (accept NavalSupportFacility Thurmont before mentioned; accept Shangri- La before mentioned) (7) A speech advocating for this action was given “at a college noted for knowledge, in a city noted for progress, in a state noted for strength.” This action was compared to “climb[ing] the highest mountain,” “fly[ing] the Atlantic,” and (+) “Rice play[ing] Texas” in a 1962 speech that noted “we choose to” do this “in this decade.” The development of the (*) Saturn V [five] propulsion system was instrumental in performing this action, which was last done by the Challenger lander in 1972. For ten points, name this exploration first done by Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong aboard Apollo 11."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "going to the Moon",
        "equivalents related to a manned Moon landing",
        "any additional information related to John F. Kennedy’s push for Americans/NASA going to the moon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After natives in what is now this country committed a ritual mass suicide known as puputan, the city of Klungkung fell to European colonists. A ruler of this country established a system called USDEK to implement (20 pts)",
        "Guided Democracy; that system fell apart after the 30 September Movement and gave way to the New Order. Mohammad Hatta served as Vice President and Prime Minister for the (10 pts)",
        "INP in, for ten points, what Asian country, once led by Sukarno and Suharto, whose capital is Jakarta?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Indonesia"
    }
  ]
}